Neil P. Speirs Collection of U.S. Railroad Retirement Board Memorabilia 6215 MB
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Neil P. Speirs Collection of U.S Railroad Retirement Board Memorabilia
1953-1977
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Speirs, Neil P.
United States. Railroad Retirement Board
6215 MB
1 cubic feet
1 linear ft.
Memorabilia.
This collection contains the memorabilia of Neil P. Speirs, former president of the Switchmsn's Union of North America [SUNA], assistant president of the United Transportation Union [UTU], and labor member of the U.S. Railroad Retirement Board.
6083415
Biographical / Historical
Neil P. Speirs was born in Alberta, Canada, on December 25, 1912 and moved to the United States with his parents in 1919. He became a naturalized citizen in 1942. Mr. Speirs graduated from the University of Idaho in 1934, having majored in business and education.
Mr. Speirs began his railroad career with Southern Pacific Railroad, working in the railroad's train yards. He was first elected to the local Grievance Committee of Adjustment for the Switchmen's Union of North America [SUNA], Local 98 (San Francisco, CA) in 1950. In 1952, he was elected as a full-time officer, serving as chairman of the General Grievance Committee of Adjustment, Southern Pacific Railroad [SP]. Mr. Speirs served in this capacity until 1955, when he was elected to serve as SUNA International Vice-President. In 1959, he was elected to be President of SUNA and served as President until January 1, 1969.
On January 1, 1969 SUNA, along with the Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen, the Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen, and the Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen formed the United Transportation Union [UTU]. Upon the merger, Mr. Speirs became Assistant President of UTU.
In 1969, President Richard Nixon appointed Mr. Speirs as the Labor Member of the Railroad Retirement Board. In 1974, President Gerald Ford re-appointed him to that position. He retired from the Railroad Retirement Board in 1977, but served on the Arbitration Panel of the National Mediation Board on a part-time basis until 1978.
Scope and Contents
Inclusive date range: 1953-1977, undated
Bulk dates: 1953-1977
This collection contains memoribilia collected by Neil P. Speirs over the course of his career. Numerous pins, both pin-back buttons and enameled stick pins, from SUNA are located in this collection. These pins either mark important milestones of Speirs' membership in SUNA or publicize SUNA initiatives and camapigns. Other SUNA memoribilia found in this collection include a commemorative plate and a zippered vinyl pouch. Because of his position as the president of SUNA and as assisstant president of UTU, Mr. Speirs also collected numerous guest badges and medals for the conventions of other unions. Also found in this collection are three enamel pins from the National Railway Workers' Union of Japan [NRU], given to Mr. Speirs during a visit NRU members made to SUNA headquarters in Buffalo, NY. A medal commemorating the founding of the UTU, with a portrait of Mr. Speirs on the front, is found in this collection. Finally, a pen used by President Lyndon B. Johnson to sign an act to facilitate research into high-speed ground transportation.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 6215: Neil P. Speirs Collection of U.S. Railroad Retirement Board Member Files 6215 P: Neil P. Speirs Collection of U.S. Railroad Retirement Board Member Photographs 5034: Switchmen's Union of North America Records 5034 MB: Switchmen's Union of North America Memorabilia 5034 P: Switchmen's Union of North America Photographs 5084: Switchmen's Union of North America Additional Records 5405 mf: Switchmen's Union of North America Constitutions on Microfilm 5406 mf: Switchmen's Union of North America Arbitration on Microfilm 5447: Switchmen's Union of North America Additional Unification Minutes and Convention Proceedings 5556: Switchmen's Union of North America Additional Records 5139: UTU Records 5139 AV: UTU Audio-Visual Material 5139 MB: UTU Memorabilia 5139 P: UTU Photographs
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives 227 Ives Hall Tower Road Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheelref@cornell.edu https://catherwood.library.cornell.edu/kheel/
Compiled by:
E. Parker, May 02, 2017
EAD encoding:
E. Parker, May 02, 2017
Speirs, Neil P.; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973; United States. Railroad Retirement Board; AFL-CIO; Gilbert, H. E.; Lane, C. F.; Gompers, Samuel, 1850-1924; Amalgamated Meat Cutters and Butcher Workmen of North America; Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employees; Brotherhood of Railway Clerks; International Brotherhood of Firemen and Oilers; Switchmen's Union of North America; United Transportation Union; Brotherhood Railway Carmen of the United States and Canada; Meany, George, 1894-1980; Schnitzler, William F.; Luna, Charles, 1906-
6083415
- Samuel Gompers Coins - Amalgamated Meat Cutters & Butcher Workmen of N.A. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  2 coins
- President Lyndon B. Johnson's Pen, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  "One of the pens used by the President, September 30, 1965, in signing S. 1588, An Act to authorize the Secretary of Commerce to undertake research and development in high-speed ground transportation, and for other purposes.
- Speirs' UTU Commemorative Medal, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  3 medals with portraits of the presidents of the four unions which united to form the UTU: N. P. Speirs, Charles Luna, H. E. Gilbert, C. F. Lane
- International Brotherhood of Firemen and Oilers special guest medal and Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen pin, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Special guest medal from the 26th Convention of the International Brotherhood of Firemen and Oilers, held in Miami Beach, Florida, May 3-7, 1971.
- Brotherhood of Railway Carmen convention guest medals, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  2 guest medals for the 25th Convention of the Brotherhood of Railroad Carmen of America, Kansas City, Missouri, July 30-August 11, 1973
- Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employees convention guest medals, 1970-1974 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Two guest medals from Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employs conventions. One is from the 36th Regular Convention, Detroit, Michigan, 1970; the other is from the 37th Regular Convention, Denver, Colorado, 1974
- UTU pins, tie clips, golf divot tool, golf ball markers (Box 1, Folder 7)
- AFL-CIO Convention Badges and cuff links, 1959-1977 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Conventions: San Francisco, California, 1959; New York, New York, 1963; San Francisco, California, 1965 (2 badges); Bal Harbour, Florida, 1967; Los Angeles, California, 1977
- SUNA - badges and pin-back buttons, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Member badge (front) Maple Leaf Lodge No. 84, Switchmen's Union of North America, Oelwein, Iowa (back) In Memoriam, Maple Leaf Lodge No. 84, Switchmen's Union of North America, Oelwein, Iowa; Vice-president badge and Delegate badge from 6th Quadrennial Convention, June, 1959; 2 pin-back buttons
- SUNA and National Railway Workers' Union of Japan [NRU] buttons, 1953-1966 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  pin-back and enamel buttons; 3 buttons from the NRU. See collection 6215 P, box 1 folder16, for a photograph of their visit to SUNA headquarters in Buffalo, NY
- SUNA plate (Box 1, Folder 11)
- SUNA zippered case (Box 1, Folder 12)
- UTU Plaque honoring N.P. Speirs on his retirement, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  see letter in collection 6215, box 1, folder 10
- N.P. Speirs stamp; UTU paper weight (Box 1, Folder 14)